we're gonna start classifier ACI it's
good to see you come from many places I
know you're working hard and okay first
question on homework fun and this is a
tough question what is sansara
what is samsara okay by the way you're
trained at ACI you're not gonna say
samsara okay in the writing it's Sam in
the pronunciation it's Sun sauna like
French you can speak French just talk to
your nose okay
so subtle so Sutter okay alright son sir
si and it's M is illegal in Sanskrit
before s it's it's it can it's a legal
incentive ahem sir it's also wrong it's
it's not allowed in Sanskrit to put an
end before an s ok so just do it right
it's one of my Masha it's a pet peeve of
mine samsara sounds like some guy from
Chicago or something ok I'd like and it
took me many years ok it's 27 years
since I wrote this course and maybe last
year I understood Sun sir what is it in
the kitchen where is the Sun Sarah in
the kitchen yeah so the the first two
husbands in the kitchen story which I
think it's gonna be you know Buddha has
a heart sutra I have two husbands in
kitchen okay
I think mine's gonna be almost as famous
so the woman yelled at her kids last
week she came home tonight
her husband yelled at her before she
said anything and then the natural
reaction is to yell back
I didn't say I didn't do anything I'm
not stupid you're stupid okay
then that actually plants a seed in her
mind which will open next week in the
kids room the kids will be bad again
then she'll yell at the kids she'll
plant a new seed one week later
yeah the husband will yell at her
because the seed open in the kitchen
right and it's a cycle you see so don't
think samsara samsara is some painting
of future life or past life okay
in the avi drama there's a catch in
matenda a chick matenda son sala by the
minute samsara by the minute you don't
need to wait for three lifetimes to have
a wheel of life okay you're doing it
every few minutes okay you are creating
cycles in English we say downward cycle
and we also say in English I don't know
how it's in your language okay but we
call self-perpetuating cycle the cycle
tends to cause itself to keep turning so
probably in your own country you have
some word like that in Chinese you have
it's a it's a circle which keeps itself
going like those old clocks where they
just keep going you know the pendulum
clock okay
circle which repeats itself okay and it
could be repeating two or three times in
a day in one day that's son sir okay so
you have little son size and you have
big sensors okay so I don't want to see
definition on the homework that oh you
die you go to another place you know
something like that okay let's be more
cool let's get it right okay you're
spinning some stars every few minutes
you are turning Sun Sarris every few
minutes you are spinning starting cycles
every few minutes okay how do you break
it wait
in the kitchen where does she break the
cycle
yeah when in the moment that she decides
not to yell okay no long June Nando
tangent d'el djem loop tangent Elgin
looked at unlimited October J that's my
trailer okay what's it mean yeah good
okay the chain reaction like you don't
understand the husband then you yell
okay first two links okay that's called
forward loom June in my trailer it's a
one two three four five six and antonyms
oh okay
but be careful when you say reverse it
because what does it mean do you go 12
11 10 nine eight
yeah good you stop one and that stops
too and that stops three and that stops
first so when they say long dog which
means reverse it don't think it's like
reversing a car you know it's not that
you go twelve eleven ten nine okay it's
that you go kill one kills to kill to
kill three kill three kill four okay got
it
you okay I can see Jasmine thinking of
some problem when it asked me later
she's too smart
okay good student London high IQ high
Dharma IQ okay so that's to me samsara
okay
by the way it's the same route sir which
means to flow okay as a nice Rana nice
runner which means renunciation flow out
or prasarita padottanasana and okay
different same route okay it means it
tends to spread like in that pose you
spread your legs and you grab your feet
if you can
huh good class today word thank you for
class I had a good I mean I had a less
terrible time okay and dresses classes
man but I felt stronger after two of
those classes I don't know but I
wouldn't do it every day okay no I don't
want to teach it easy class like I'm not
hinting I want a tough class from you
but I want to complain about it because
it's fun to complain okay second
question on homework five what is me
none say Y is renunciation necessary to
escape the cycle of life and then the
second question is what's the
relationship between the first principle
path and the second principle time okay
and let's answer the first question
first okay and and it's always a
metaphor it's a certain metaphor which
is used in Buddhism which is yeah Jo if
you don't realize you're in jail you
don't want to break on if you don't
realize you're in the prison you won't
want to get out okay so this is kind of
duh you're in prison man okay if you
don't know you're in prison or you can't
realize you're in prison then you're not
going to try to reach nirvana and
Buddhahood okay if you don't recognize
the pain of this whole world constant
pain every minute of every living
creature from bugs to humans you won't
want to get out of it okay so a lot of
people are just like I don't know there
was a famous student of Milarepa and his
name is Gump oppa and he was a medical
doctor and that's the first book I ever
studied by the way with Gidget with I
guess she was calm Papa's text and GaN
Popo was married and he was a doctor and
his wife died
and then he he was like extremely sad
but he said at least now I'm free to go
you know practice hard in a cave or
something this is Miller interesting
right so he hurt her uncle came to visit
him after she passed away and he's like
I'm so sorry your wife died and he says
sorry are you kidding
it's wonderful and then the uncle took
some dirt and Stewart just threw it in
his face and it's a famous story and of
course it's not a wonderful thing but
he's just saying now I have a chance he
recognized the suffering of life and I
think it's kind of like kids who grow up
with money kids who grew up with a lot
of money in my experience in my long
experience many times it ruins them they
don't learn how to work they don't know
what it's like to work they run out of
money and then they don't know how to
work and they they have trouble I've
seen it many times because I worked in
the diamond business many of the kids
were rich and when my friend's son was
married in Mumbai they rented the
Mumbai's soccer stadium they invited
60,000 people they threw diamonds out
the window on the way to the stadium but
those kids are unhappy you see those
kids never learn to work and they have a
weird life and then when they run out of
money they have a very hard life why am
I talking about that if you're lucky
somebody will die close to you or your
country will be bombed and you see what
life really is while you're still young
and then you have time to do something
about it start refugee projects
something like that okay understand
you're lucky to have some problems in
your life because life is problems and
if you don't know
you won't learn what to do okay you
won't have an incision so if you don't
know you're in the jail you don't want
to get out okay we teach DCI we're
teaching people five goals financial
freedom good partner good health
peaceful mind help the world but really
the first three or four you have to lose
them you know it doesn't matter if you
get money it doesn't matter if you get a
nice house it doesn't matter if you
marry somebody you're gonna lose
everything okay that's what we tell them
in the ACI course so ACI is more
advanced in teeth the best teachers
teach for a CEO okay no AC ice scope is
is beyond this name and this isotope is
not okay so actually your scope is
bigger okay all right hmm
then I was studying lower-middle way
with my teacher
there's a famous topic called LOM top
tool it's almost a so cool guess it is a
circle and it's about the five paths you
write give me a mantra got a got a para
got a para Sangha body so ha five five
pass yeah all these TSP people know
everything okay
so yeah then what's the first cut day
yeah a big problem in your life disaster
in your life you know for me as you know
half my family died in one year and you
wake up it's a win English we say
wake-up call
you're like oh wow life is hard like
there's something going on here okay now
there's three tracks there's actually 15
paths five five and five okay so that's
a lower-middle way okay because they say
there's three degrees of emptiness
there's an easy emptiness there's a
medium emptiness difficult emptiness
okay
difficult emptiness is for Bodhisattvas
then the other two tracks are for lower
way people okay who don't want to be
Bodhisattva okay and they actually see
different kinds of emptiness according
to lower mentally which is not true
according to the higher middle way in
the higher middle way if you see
emptiness directly it's always the same
emptiness that the Buddha is seeing
right now okay and you don't see it any
better than a Buddha does sorry
a Buddha doesn't see it any better than
you do a person who just saw emptiness
for the first time directly is seeing
100% what a Buddha sees for those 20
minutes okay so don't think it's
different it's the same there's no
degrees you either see it or you don't
see it okay why are we talking about
that the entry point for the highest
five path is not personal disaster it's
one bodhichitta it's the desire to
become enlightened to help the universe
okay got it
lower tracks fire paths you enter the
first path when you have a personal
disaster like your wife does okay then
you get interested in religion okay but
the highest chart it's not personal
disaster anymore you only get into the
highest five path the beginning is you
want to become a Buddha to help
everybody bodhichitta you get
bodhichitta wish for enlightenment okay
therefore it's not the same as
bodhichitta is not the same as yeah good
direct perception emptiness okay it's
possible to be a bodhisattva before you
see emptiness directly okay so it's not
true that all Bodhisattvas saw emptiness
directly okay the ones who started on
the first path second path
they are bodhisattva but they didn't see
emptiness directly what's the second
path in DCI
yeah geshe-la drives you crazy teach you
the pen again it's actually second path
okay
second time okay now I remember I didn't
have a dictionary for 25 years I had my
llama and so I would just ask him what's
this mean you know but to be honest he
wasn't dying to answer questions and I
had to bribe him all the time constant
process
I collect my questions if I ask him you
know some questions just shut up you
know and don't bother me you know but
then I make Momo for him which I'm gonna
do forget you don't arm and if you make
mom or your llama he answered all your
questions and what you do is you hold
the plane and you say I have question
and he's like yeah yeah what's the
question and I said you know Rinpoche in
the lower five pass you first pass you
have to have a disaster your mother has
to die but then in the third pass it's
so different you just have to want to
become a Buddha you see it's so
different you know why is that
I said why he said I give me the most
that's an easy question
buddy China is a disaster for everybody
it's just the same disaster but it's
it's everybody's disaster you see you're
not just thinking about your mother time
you're thinking everybody's mother time
that's all history is the same thing
it's just personal disaster times the
zillion you know in this world personal
disaster times seven billion that's but
it's the same thing got it everyone's
mother gonna die okay so if you think
like that you entered the first path on
the higher chart but it's a fit check
got it that's the relationship between
the first principal path and the second
principal path and you have to put it on
your homework okay I'm bribing you
that's my mo
for you okay
now something about love em okay the
word love me it can refer to all the
steps of the path from the day your
mother dies up till the day you become a
Buddha all the steps it's called the lam
rim okay got it
but each step is also called Lam rim a
long rim okay this is the long room and
it has a long rims
okay so steps a step a step a step a
step and then the whole thing together
is called steps but the Tibetan is the
same that is the tetanus is same and
it's confusing when you're a translator
which lamrim are you working on you say
I'm working on three principal paths
know which lung room are you working on
oh I'm studying how to how to find a
teacher okay I'm like at the beginning
I'm studying how to find a teacher
okay got it why did I say that two
famous LOM rims meaning two famous steps
relate to renunciation okay stop desire
for this life
okay get you thinking about next line
okay they say get your thinking bigger
than this life to of the long rims two
of the steps are connected to sagan nice
I know you got one of them say Chiwa
meet Appa to our meet Appa which is a
confusing Tibetan word and it means
impermanence in the form of death okay
so just it's a difficult to button
impermanence in the form of death but
before that tangent near car down Jordan
Cheney Erica I'm so lucky
okay leisure and fortune we call leisure
and fortune I got
all the chance I need to become a Buddha
I got a human body I got a good mind
I got teachers I got good translations I
got friends who want to go there to like
I everything sent for me I have
everything I need
okay good chance call it good chance
okay so good chance and death are two
two meditations two steps of the Lamia
that relate to stop thinking about this
life start thinking about next line okay
in the lamrim teachings you're not a
Buddhist you're not practicing Buddhism
and tell your thinking about your next
life
that's very radical okay it means DCI
none of it is Buddhism okay technically
okay very interesting you're not
practicing Buddhism until your
motivation touches on what's going to
happen to you after you die okay
in technically technically in Buddhism
I'll tell you start thinking about your
next life and taking care of that trip
that you have to make okay like if you
know you have to come to Diamond
Mountain we have a rule in DCI nobody
follows it but you know it's one of
those rules always packed 48 hours
before you leave okay there laughing
always packed 48 hours before you leave
why because you're so stressed out
afternoon you got a you know somebody's
got to take care of the dog you got to
clean out the refrigerator there's a
thousand things you have to do so you
know you have to go that the DCI
schedule is published on the design
website people always asking me get out
what is this I schedule they won't give
it to me I ask Connery they said it's on
the internet it's on the website look on
the website okay we didn't put together
we didn't put your personal holidays
like Veronica's birthday we didn't put
that on okay so there's a few days you
can't see on the website but the rest
are there okay don't don't whine to me
okay so what was I talking about
yeah so logically if you're a Buddhist
logician which none of us are you would
pack two days before because you know
you have to go and you know what you
have to take and you're not gonna wear a
suit at home anyway okay
never ever that's one of my mama's
favorite expressions never ever so pack
your suits get him in the suitcase do it
finish okay get it ready you know I get
it all packed and I leave it open for my
toothbrush and you know some clean
underwear because I have to do the
laundry because I didn't do it for three
weeks and okay so the whole suitcase is
ready why am I talking about that yeah
get ready just get ready now take care
of it now okay take care of your next
life now okay then you don't have to
worry you get hit by a car you're ready
you don't get hit by a car you're ready
so take care of it now
okay do what you have to do to have a
good day and go to the right place
what's the insurance policy for what's
the insurance policy suitcase you should
pack before you die understand the pen
clearly you know also with regard to
yourself okay
not just pens you know hold up the pen
with your arms sometimes she keeps
giving me pens you must be running out
you know I tell I started telling people
in DC I audiences if you understand the
pen
people complain to me especially a
certain city in South Asia
it starts with singing and ends with
poor okay and okay the guy was not from
Singapore I have to say he was from
Europe but he bitterly complained to me
why you keep repainting this pen you
know we have to pay every time we have
to pay for the same thing every time I
said to him I said you didn't understand
it the first time that's why I have to
prove
repeat it but or the first ten times but
nowadays I tell people the truth which
is if you understand the pen well your
suitcase is packed you don't have to
worry about dying you will come back to
this crappy world okay but at least you
won't go to the hell okay and you won't
be an animal impossible not physically
possible okay if you understand
conquering emptiness clearly especially
about your arm and the pen these are the
same then you it's impossible to take a
lower breath that burns if anger burns
bad sees pen burns sorry anger burns
good sees pen burns bad sees okay
pen burns the seeds that take you to a
lower birth okay got it
so that's a Lamia right I'm so lucky I
have a chance now but chew Amitabha okay
and what's the what's a real death
meditation what I mean before we get to
it
what's death militaria what's a simple
way to do death meditation everyday when
you brush your teeth and you see this
handsome guy in the mirror I mean it's
not true for everybody but that's me and
jump ready you know when you're brushing
your teeth just say I'm gonna die today
I'm gonna go to do okay because one day
it will be true okay so why not get
ready pack your bag in the morning I'm
gonna die today
you know do I really want to waste time
today or do I have some cool plants
today do I have some fun Dharma plans
for today of course you have to go to
work of course you have to take care of
your family but while you're brushing
your teeth I'm gonna die today
I'm gonna pack my bag I'm gonna get
things ready okay I'm gonna think about
the pen today or I'm gonna read reread a
CI course number one make sure I got it
straight like that guess II who had the
logic book on his chest in the hospital
on the day he died
okay like you should have your a CI
teacher training manual on your your lap
your phone should be on your chest okay
so that's a death meditation that's a
real death meditation it's not like you
sit down and your head falls apart you
know it sounds very sexy right very
mysterious very mystical you know death
meditation - meditation is toothbrush
meditation okay it's not more mystical
than that when you brush your teeth in
the morning say I'm good dry and this
stuff will come out and that's a good
sign okay all right I'm gonna die so
those are the first two steps of the
path that relate to not being attached
to this line okay pack your bag do the
toothbrush meditation and recognize you
have a great chance you have a great
chance and by the way don't think don't
start tomorrow
start today okay because you may lose
the chance like that lady who got cancer
last week she was totally healthy two
weeks ago she was normal
the whole family she's totally normal
did she feel like a little bit sick then
they do a MRI she cut tumors everywhere
she died a few days ago you know we
don't know right it's kind of what would
set it in yoga class we don't know
what's going on in our body our own body
we don't know what's going on
so get ready now pack the bag now you
know you gotta go
so do your pen learn your pen learn the
pen well get ready get the backpack okay
then if you get hit by a truck you're
like no problem my back your friends are
all like ah you're like ah it's okay my
bag is packed get ready now okay I told
you that no one's gonna do it but at
least I told you okay
and think about how lucky you are things
are not gonna get easier for your
Buddhist practice next week or next
month or next year forget it okay I'm
telling you from sixty six get your
kicks on Route 66 you get busier every
year not less busy every year okay you
have more commitments every year okay
not less commitments kids have kids kids
kids have kids you know things pile up
okay your life will be more complicated
next year then this year unless you die
okay got it
so don't think you're gonna have more
time next year start your practice
tomorrow do your practice tomorrow cut
cut the time out for your meditation
tomorrow okay you're lucky you got
everything don't tell people under you
know my hair fell out in the middle the
girls don't look at me anymore you know
don't worry about your life you are so
goddamn lucky you know the people in
this room you are one person in a
hundred million you really are okay
everybody has to die
everybody has to pack their bags in
Arizona right now you're the only 60
people who are hearing about how to pack
your bag trust me
I believe that okay got it don't tell me
yo I'm five pounds overweight or you
know I can't find the perfect shoes that
I've been looking for I'm not so you are
goddamn lucky okay you're here alright
you are one in a hundred million you
must be pretty cool or you're here by
accident and no no such thing in
Buddhism alright if you're here you are
extremely special person and you should
teach special people should teach okay
so those are two
Lahm rims to prevent you from being too
attached to this life okay and that's
one toothbrush meditation in God right
now everything's right I'm healthy you
know my mind is clear I got a pretty
decent family life yeah everything's my
country allows me to do things I'm
pretty everything's cool let me get it
done now let me pack my bag now okay I'm
really special I'm really lucky okay
I'll tell you something cool about
Tibetan medicine so I translate it for
the two most famous Tibetan doctors for
about five years whenever they came to
the US I transcended for them and I
learned a lot and this one doctor yes he
done them he said the most amazing thing
he said you have this what do you call
it
doshas and what's the other one goodness
you have these energies in your body for
example heat bile wind and was it Loum
phlegm you have this hot power in your
body you have cool power in your body
for example okay so like the body is
breathing to keep the body cool okay
and it's competing with the circulation
system the lungs are competing with the
heart the lungs job in Tibetan medicine
Chinese medicine is to keep your body
from getting too hot and the purpose of
the heart is to keep the body from
getting too cold so actually in your
body is two forces that are fighting
with each other from the moment you are
born and health is an accident in
Ayurveda health is an accident okay
health is like did you really like I
don't know throw a toothpick on the
table and it stand up
and you're like oh my god you know or
your coin you drop a coin and it lands
on the Sun and it's and it goes like
this it stays that's that's health
that's to be healthy it's unusual it's
abnormal sickness is normal human
condition health is abnormal health is a
coin that landed on this side and stayed
there okay I'll let go the toothpick
okay it didn't really happen
coin can happen right so health is an
accident and and sooner or later one of
the if the cooling element gets stronger
you get pneumonia if the heating element
gets stronger you have a heart attack
sooner or later one of them will get
stronger okay
they will fight they'll punch it out and
one will get stronger and you will die
okay
why am I talking about that you have a
chance right now in your life you got
everything you got good teaching good
solid teaching you got really senior
teachers spent 40 years meditating spent
did the three-year retreat do their
practice every day understand emptiness
you got diamond mountain you know you
got everything come on
okay and it won't last okay it's like a
coin on the side okay it's gonna fall
down okay use it I used to go borrow
books from my teacher he he didn't like
to loan books he's like very cheap with
his books you know but I remember he
gave me a book and he said use it don't
lose it I think that's the last word he
ever said to me he'd passed away after
them and I kept the book but he said use
it don't lose it okay human bonnie ACI
courses Diamond Mountain okay use it
don't lose it
all right mmm say jig then you're gay
very very very famous in Buddhism's what
is that yeah you can say it will the
dumbest show means Darmouth but in this
case it means attitude perfect eight
different attitudes so these are called
eight worldly attitudes there are famous
in Buddhist in Buddhism so you should
know them if you're an ACI teacher you
should know that the eight worldly
attitudes there's eight worldly
attitudes okay and we're gonna go
through them now okay and they come from
the guardian of Sulekha letter to a
friend you can find them in there okay
and we should study that sometime we
should go through it there's a beautiful
commentary by tsongkhapa's teacher
Randhawa sakya okay here we go number
one okay number one of what eight
worldly attitudes okay Nia Kurt Juna gah
okay happy you got something okay
someone gives you a red envelope and you
like wow I got a rhythm you know my
teacher I don't know what happened a
demon bought him a television I really
believe it was a demon and actually some
weird weird thing happened and I I saw a
demon in this person and he bought him a
television and he started watching
baseball all the time and like every day
you know and I wasn't really sure he was
watching the TV because his monitors
were going and sometimes you would he'd
say turn the TV off and you take real
much a look about to say who killed the
guy in the next two minutes he said turn
so I was never sure he was watching it I
thought maybe it was for me to make me
feel comfortable with this foreigner you
know he watches American TV he must be
normal you know so anyway so some guy
would hit a home run you know he make a
good play and he'd go like this they
closed up on the baseball players face
and he's like aah and repete said world
apartment number one right there right
there
he's always teaching me he said oh
that's number one that's number one that
right there okay
and it's always followed by yeah that at
the end of the game he drops the ball
everyone hates him in the whole stadium
and he's like dude you know and remember
say said perfect number one and to every
baseball player perfect number one and
number two they do something good
they're like ah all the fans are also
number one and number two oh you're so
great it's so great you know
then he messed up anyone's blue boot
they throw things at him and they throw
beer bottles and stuff they stopped
serving beer and bottles or baseball
games so that's one and two okay
something nice happens you get something
like a new car somebody gives you a new
car and you're like ah okay then next
day you scratch it somebody in the
parking lot that's in America they
scratch your car and they run away and
you come out of the grocery store and
there's a big scratch in your car and
then you're like this okay
those aren't two non-buddhists attitudes
okay don't get too happy if something
goes right and don't get too sad okay
from 66 not from 71 I don't know about
271 guys but from 66 I can tell you
something
stuffs gonna mess up in your life
sometimes don't take it too seriously
okay your problems are not the biggest
problems in this room forget it they're
probably the smallest problems in this
room okay the person next to you they
have cancer their mother died yesterday
come on you have a scratch in your car
okay take it easy okay from 66 I'm
telling you right Kelsey diamond
mountain director by the way the diamond
mountain director is going to be
retiring to work harder in Sedona and
I'd like to give her a hand and we're
gonna have a small party for her
[Music]
[Applause]
and there's a big fool called
sinem who agreed to be the new director
we should give her so we're very lucky
anyway don't get from 66 I'm telling you
look sometimes bad stuff happens okay
sometimes we had bad stuff here we had
very serious best stuff here it happens
in your life
stuff happens okay don't freak out don't
give up your Buddhism don't get all sad
okay this is the eight worldly attitude
you know stuff goes wrong okay life
doesn't go perfect
you have good seeds you have bad seeds
in your head already okay so don't get
all serious okay have fun go out and
look at the scratch on your car interior
oh man that's such a scratch you know
and you have a choice right you you
always have a choice you can be sad you
can be here number two you can do number
two you could tell everybody for three
days actually nobody cares okay that's
the other thing don't talk about your
problems nobody cares
oh my car got scratched oh I'm so sad
I'm so sorry
but not really I don't you have anything
else to talk about
did anything nice happen today okay by
the way your students as a a CI teacher
to tell you the truth they're not
interested in your problems okay so
don't waste their time and don't waste
your time okay funny thing happens to me
when I go to teach in some countries two
three thousand people will come and a
thousand will line up for for a
signature and I feel like they really
like me
and I'm famous and I feel pretty good
3,000 people in the audience you know
and they're all waiting for two hours to
get their book signed you know and
sometimes this very lovely lady will
come up and we always take a picture
they always sit next to me
you know and we take a picture you know
and I was like wow all the most
beautiful women in Taiwan want to sit
next to Geshe Michael you know and they
take the picture and then I have a smile
ready and I go like this and they're
already walking away you know I'm like
you know they just want the picture okay
your students don't really care about
your personal life okay if games you
might gonna have a heart attack after
the photo it's okay so don't get all
this thing about you know you want to
hear about my car got scratched or you
want to hear about this blue car my
students gave me as a teacher they don't
want to hear about you they're there for
themself they want you to help them you
see what I mean it's they're not coming
there to tell you how cool you are
they're coming there because they got
cancer okay I translated for you she
didn't about a hundred people came to
the talk it was a normal audience just
like this you know it was an auntie
Karen's house Alice was in her arms
she's our accountant okay she's probably
40 no she has her own kid
right so she was in Nancy's arms this is
how long ago I was strengthening and and
the doctor finished the whole teaching
you know it was very beautiful and then
he announced if and it was a normal room
like this he said if anyone in this room
has an extremely serious medical
condition come tomorrow to this address
and I will treat you for free you know
very famous doctor the most famous
doctor in Tibet probably and so I
thought okay
he said can you translate I said well
you know I got to go to work but it's
gonna be early right he said yeah it'll
be early like seven o'clock I said okay
I can do like probably going to be five
six people I could I can do it every
person in the room showed up I'd say 90%
of these normal people had a serious
medical condition and they're just
barely standing up you see I mean but
they look normal
okay so you go on the subway you go on
the airplane you see a airplane full of
normal people half of them are very sick
okay you just don't know so don't a
teacher don't bore them with your
problems they don't really care okay and
I don't mean they're they don't love you
they love you
but they have problems of their own and
they have serious problems and the
reason they came to you is to help them
with their problems not your problem
okay so don't waste your time go whine
to your teacher about your promise okay
that's cool that's okay that's what your
teacher is for and if they're a real
teacher when they make a commitment to
you it's not for one lifetime you can
whine from multiple lifetimes okay got
it and they will not give you up that's
the last great quality of a of a teacher
okay so once you have a real teacher you
have a winnable available Y Noble okay
but don't bother your students they
don't care okay really don't don't tell
them all your problems and stuff like
that okay if you want to use your
problems as an example that's okay I
have jealousy it's my second worst clay
sure what's that joke about yeah guys I
will always tell you the second worst
one but he's so embarrassed about the
first first one he will never mention it
and that's the same with everybody in
this room okay the worst one you don't
want to tell anybody because you're
embarrassed but my number one my number
two is jealousy
okay that you can say that you can say
in the class that's honest right I have
a problem with jealousy okay
Guerra we're so happy in Singapore what
this teacher came he's like trained in
Buddhist monastery he's a foreigner it's
a very handsome also I'm like oh I'm so
happy
ok so those are the first two what you
saw me do that why are you laughing so
hard okay number three now this is
really hard there's a joke in Tibetan
okay word 100 bucks not Nanak any devil
motto not non and cubed mo much and you
got to get every word nan nan na kehna
devilment you yeah good
cancel that shopping no money no money
honey okay ever since I got sick I
haven't felt well ever since I got sick
I haven't felt well it's a joke
ever since I got sick I didn't feel well
does it make sense what it means is ok
here's what the meaning is especially as
a teacher as a teacher
some days you're teaching in pain okay
some days you're teaching in pain yoga
teacher also you know and you just do it
that's my deep advice for a CI teacher
okay some days your your girlfriend just
left you that afternoon or your company
went bankrupt or the doctor told you you
got a big cancer in your leg or
something yeah and you don't feel well
you have a headache you feel sick okay
but here totally happy okay big smile
they say gig loud how do you feel
you're like I feel great how's it going
fantastic you know you know and you're
in great pain like you have a very bad
headache or you didn't sleep last night
a teacher has to get through that a
teacher has to work through that you
I'll tell you something about famous
people like famous musicians or
something one of the things that makes
them famous is they came to the concert
okay that's one of the things to be a
really famous musician or a famous actor
you have to come to the movie set or you
have to come to the concert when you
don't feel well okay and you don't feel
like it you feel sad or you feel sick
and you're you know okay who was there
in Guadalajara I gave a talk yeah and I
said I have to finish ten minutes early
I think hustle was it I don't remember I
ran to the door and I I threw up not
like I threw up like blue
and I was totally sick I held it the
whole talk and I'm very cheerful you
know and then I said good night I had to
finish a little early and I kind of
walked fast in the door and then right
on the other side of the door okay it
wasn't like dribble out it was like
projection like future life karma okay
so number three you know if you feel
healthy if you feel like you just
finished undress class and you feel
strong and happy that it finished and
don't get too excited okay don't worry
you will break something tomorrow
you'll catch something tomorrow don't
get too excited when you're feeling good
oh look I lost five pounds
trust me ten will come back this is
another 66 thing right JB every time you
lose 510 comes back I don't know what it
is okay
don't get too excited when you're
feeling good okay it's gonna change
accepting use it be happy
be grateful but don't get too attached
to it because it will change and that's
number what are we on for now before is
when you get sick especially as a
teacher don't whine don't tell people
again very few people care in the
audience they're there to listen to how
you're going to help them they're not
there to hear about your medical
condition okay so a good teacher a good
musician a good movie actor they learn
to to do their thing under in paint okay
when they don't feel so well okay
there's days when you won't want to do
your yoga David Swensen you know him
it's like there's days when you feel
like a bag of wet cement but do your
practice okay do your practice okay
ignore how you feel I got it
that's three and four don't get too
attached to how you feel
work through it okay if you cancel
things because you don't feel well
you'll have to cancel everything
eventually okay if you don't meditate
cuz your legs hurt what's gonna happen
ten years from now
you think it's gonna magically get
younger it will it could okay anyway
alright number five you get famous for
something you know they write you about
you in tricycle magazine there's a
beautiful article about this law you can
find it in the old magazine there's a
long article he's so amazing teacher he
did the ACI courses he understands
diamond cutting
that's that picture cutting diamond came
from there
and then you feel like wow I'm really
something you know boy did I give a talk
yesterday in English about abhidharma
three different source languages sounds
good too man and Chinese and people
claps boy I must have been about twenty
minutes and so you get some little fame
okay now trust me next week something
Bad's gonna happen and everybody will be
criticizing you on the internet the
whole world it happens okay they say
keep your head down if you don't want
trouble like don't don't put your head
up star my head up like don't become a
teacher
because the minute you become a teacher
that demons will they're looking for who
puts their head up you know who wants to
do something important in this world
then the demons pay attention to you
right if you just took quiet and watch
TV
demons never bother you okay but the
minute you try to do acip
or a CI or DCI or the amount something
will happen
okay and don't freak out about it okay
it's called Fame or not Fame there's a
word you know in english famous right
there's the mother the sister word which
is infamous different accent famous and
then infamous and it means opposite of
famous everyone criticizes you everyone
says you're a bad person okay you're
gonna get both if you're an ACI teacher
okay just plan on it
okay remember the night that geshe-la
told you okay worldly attitude number
five and six okay gets a lot predicted
one week after you get famous for your
I'll be dumb and talk somebody
criticizes you on the internet like be
some newspaper and tell us a bad story
about you and and 1 million people read
it okay it happens like that okay and
I'm telling you from 66 I've had ball
okay I've had both I've been the
Congress of Mexico gave me a PhD you
know in the Congress and then I've been
criticized by the highest people in the
world and just let it go what are you
gonna do quit teaching you gonna go home
and cry you know you know you're gonna
give up Dharma teaching
come on what are you gonna do you're
gonna quit because someone criticize you
on the Internet
okay so get ready now before you become
a teacher get ready now worldly attitude
number five will be not a Latina
mistakes if everyone says you're a
wonderful teacher we love you please
teach us forever if they take a vow in
front of you I will serve you forever
don't get too excited just say okay
thanks I really appreciate it and then
next week they're gonna criticize you
okay and get used to it
your job as a teacher is not to be
famous and it's not to be praised
okay it's the serve people and you can
serve people who hate you okay if
someone criticizes you you can still
serve them and it's kind of cool
I had a lama who said the best way to
hurt someone who doesn't like you is to
serve them they hate it okay send them
money you know stuff like that
it's the most irritating thing god I
criticize him for two years on the
internet and now he made a donation you
know I hate this guy so if you really
want to hurt your enemies
send them donations support their
projects okay got it
as a DCI teacher a CI teacher you will
have periods in your life when you get
famous and with you know and then
there'll be periods in your life when
people criticize you online for example
and just expect it and don't get to keep
your heart steady keep your heart steady
I'm sick oh I'm sick oh I just took
Andres class I feel like a million
dollars yeah calm down you're gonna get
sick later okay
like just keep your mind don't get too
excited don't get too son okay stuffs
gonna happen okay sixty-six right what
are you can I ask hey give me five I
mean give me six this is Chinese first
six yeah all the smart people are six to
six so just calm down okay
make your attitude equal level okay
don't get too excited don't get too soon
okay about anything
I don't care what it is alright I have
stood in the White House and the
president United State has given me a
medal and I've been criticized by some
of the highest spiritual people in the
world let it go okay just keep
serve people okay it doesn't matter if
they like you or they don't they will
still take your money okay
just certain people okay got it and it's
that's the only way to have fun in this
life
I'm from 66 I'm telling you okay keep
your mind level don't get too excited
it starts hailing in the summer at
Diamond Mountain just calm down
tomorrow will be stunning and you'll be
complaining about how dry it is okay
number seventeen eight okay and this is
similar five and six were you get famous
or you get infamous on the Internet okay
like that seven and eight is people
praise you or people criticize you it's
a little bit different right you get
famous or people crit or praise you it's
not quite this thing okay people say oh
you're so smart you know you you know
all this stuff you're so smart okay then
next week they tell you how stupid you
are okay and just if you're a Buddhist
keep your mind
steady okay keep your mind straight
don't get all excited when they give you
a PhD and don't get all excited when
they tell how much they hate you okay
why your job is to serve people it
doesn't matter what they think okay
serve them secretly that's really
satisfying okay serve your enemies
secretly okay I grew up in the Christian
Church and I grew up in a church called
Episcopal Church of England and the
prayer-book the 1921 prayer book the old
prayer book
many people said it was written by
Shakespeare it's unbelievably beautiful
it's unbelievably beautiful prayer-books
I grew up with this purple you know and
and in the church they said a lot of
people thought it was written by
Shakespeare but it was written by
somebody else Archbishop of Canterbury
something but and I looked him up
because I was curious because when I
translated the VGO Guinea son which is
about a two-hour ritual I wanted to make
it beautiful like that so I got
interested in him I also sent the
manuscript to Ursula Le Guin and asked
her to fix it and she refused I asked it
it I told her I will come to you I will
rent a house next to you and I will only
come over when you're convenient for you
and you helped me make this into some
beautiful science fiction thing because
she's the most famous science fiction
writer and she said no and then I sent
her a big rod diamond and I said some
diamonds need cutting and she sent it
back to me then she died anyway not
because of that I get there much later
ok why am I talking about that yeah so
there's an interesting story about the
author of the prayer book it became
public knowledge that you should try to
be as enemy because he believes so much
in Jesus's teaching that he tried to
serve his enemies first so he will give
money to his enemies he will make them
famous he will buy them dinner they said
if you really want to be happy in London
and I don't know 18-something become
this guy's enemy because he will serve
you because you're his enemy got it
so people attack you people say you're a
lousy ACI teacher the best thing to do
is serve them
quietly anonymously okay if you serve
them and they know about it you're just
trying to piss them off come on
okay serve them people criticize you at
work people criticize your family find
ways to serve them and you will never
fall into this eight you will never fall
into this eight okay serve people
whether they like you or not and that's
your job as a a CI teacher
your job is service it's not the beard
people to like you and it's a hard from
66 right JB it's still true from 71 it's
a hard mountain to climb over okay it
takes time to learn this attitude you
know I'm gonna serve you whether you
like me or not and I'm gonna serve you
whether you praise me or not I'm gonna
serve you whether you pay for the class
or I have to pay for the class I paid
for a lot of classes in my life millions
of dollars okay just serve okay if they
don't help it's okay just serve them
that's your job
okay got it and I'll tell you something
it's the most fun life there is just
serving people who hate you it's the
most fun thing in the world okay and I
do I look like a sad person it's just
fun okay so get in the habit okay serve
everybody okay and don't don't worry
about these eight okay don't worry about
these things
you're gonna go up and down your bad
seats good seats you have a whole mix in
your bank account don't get so worried
about it keep us steady mine okay got it
that completes class five year
[Applause]